<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-31T22:04:58-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Rob Porter</title><subtitle>Digital Naturalist</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Evening Grosbeaks: Where are they now?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/evgr-pufi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evening Grosbeaks: Where are they now?" /><published>2016-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/evgr-pufi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/evgr-pufi/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;In 2015, I took on the role of coordinator &amp;amp; compiler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hamiltonnature.org/birding/counts/christmas-bird-count/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count (CBC)&lt;/a&gt;. Since that time I’ve been poring through the vast amounts of data accumulated over the decades. In a series of short posts, I explore how the Christmas Bird Count records can reveal some interesting facts about bird species in Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you speak to anyone who has been engaged with the Christmas Bird Count in Southern Ontario for more than twenty years, and ask about what they miss the most about the earlier counts, there’s a good chance the subject of grosbeaks will come up. There was a time when the large yellow Evening Grosbeaks, and sometimes their pinkish cousins the Pine Grosbeak were bound to show up in healthy sized flocks for the winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those times appear to have passed, though it isn’t entirely clear yet why that is, though there are many theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/evgr-pufi.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/evgr-pufi.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count records, 1953-2015.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, from the 1960s through the mid-1980s, most years had Evening Grosbeaks counted, and some of those years numbered in the hundreds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a comparison, the Purple Finch (another “winter finch”), has seen decline but not as extreme as Evening Grosbeaks. Between 1990 and 2010, only two Evening Grosbeaks were counted. Purple Finches have seen many “single digit” years but few years without any count at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Purple Finch observations may also be artificially lowered due to the recent over-abundance of the similar-looking introduced species House Finch.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/purple-finch.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/purple-finch.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Purple Finch, Sulphur Spring Conservation Area, Hanover, Ontario&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where did the Evening Grosbeaks go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some theories are pointing to the warmer winters – the Evening Grosbeak need not come as far south anymore to survive the winter. Certainly there’s been a noted increase in winter populations in the “cottage country” regions of Ontario, with many more of these grosbeaks appearing at feeders than ever had previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible that the feeders themselves are partly responsible. With the greatly increased human population of the Muskokas and surrounding regions, the number of feeders must have certainly gone up dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other possibility is that the population(s) of Evening Grosbeaks that once visited Southern Ontario in flocks has been either wiped out or greatly diminished, leaving the only visitors either migrants that are headed further south to upstate New York or vagrants that have strayed from their flocks. This wouldn’t be unprecidented: winter populations of Field Sparrows, Eastern Meadowlarks, and White-winged Crossbills once were quite common and are now gone or very sporatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some hope of their return. In 2014-2015, a small flock overwintered in Toronto’s High Park bird sanctuary, and that same year saw 6 of these grosbeaks counted in the Hamilton CBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the over 250 species I’ve seen within Hamilton, Evening Grosbeak is not one of them. I’m hoping soon that changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/evening-grosbeak2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/evening-grosbeak2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Evening Grosbeak, High Park, Toronto, Ontario&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Christmas Bird Count" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="Evening Grosbeak" /><category term="Purple Finch" /><category term="Hamilton&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="Toronto&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="bird records" /><summary type="html">A once-abundant winter finch has all but dissapeared from Hamilton.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Invasion of the European Starlings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016-cbc-stats-eust/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Invasion of the European Starlings" /><published>2016-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016-cbc-stats-eust</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016-cbc-stats-eust/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;In 2015, I took on the role of coordinator &amp;amp; compiler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hamiltonnature.org/birding/counts/christmas-bird-count/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count (CBC)&lt;/a&gt;. Since that time I’ve been poring through the vast amounts of data accumulated over the decades. In a series of short posts, I explore how the Christmas Bird Count records can reveal some interesting facts about bird species in Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;european-starlings&quot;&gt;European Starlings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now you likely know the stories about how European Starlings came to invade North America. What you may not know however, is how incredibly dominant this species was, and how populations of starlings have begun to drop to much more reasonable sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-years-it-was-almost-the-christmas-starling-count&quot;&gt;Some years it was almost the Christmas Starling Count…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/eust-total.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that chart is &lt;strong&gt;European Starlings&lt;/strong&gt; vs &lt;strong&gt;all bird species counted&lt;/strong&gt; during the Hamilton CBCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some observations about just how massive their numbers have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From 1967 through the early 1990s, starlings accounted for over two-thirds of all birds counted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At their peak year of 1980, starlings accounted for 73,000 out of the 93,000 birds counted – that leaves only 20,000 birds that were not starlings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since 1955, starlings accounted for almost a half of all birds ever counted: 1.5 million out of 3.4 million&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The very first count to include the European Starling was one lone bird in 1924; within four years there were over 1700 counted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, these ratios hold true even when accounting for volunteer count hours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/eust-per-hour.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The populations have dropped though since the 1990s, settling down to being between 10-15% of the overall count. This is a much more reasonable population, considering starlings are species well known to accumulate in very large flocks, especially in winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since European Starlings have been so dominant in the count in some years, it is worth taking a look at what the count looks like without them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These charts show the total count without any starlings, followed by the per-hour rate of birds counted each year excluding starlings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/eust-without.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/eust-without-per-hour.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reveals that non-starling populations actually significantly increased in the late 1990s and early 2000s, and are currently in a general decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someday soon I’ll need to see if I can assemble a similar chart of non-indigenous species (NIS) vs indigenous species. Rock Piegons, House Finches, House Sparrows, and &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; Canada Geese (not NIS, but are re-introduced and arguably invasive) are just a few possible species to compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/european-starling.jpg&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Christmas Bird Count" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="European Starling" /><category term="Hamilton&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="bird records" /><summary type="html">A look at the populations of European Starlings in Hamilton throughout the history of the Christmas Bird Count.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hamilton CBC Head to Head: Kinglets &amp;amp; Creepers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hamilton CBC Head to Head: Kinglets &amp; Creepers" /><published>2016-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;In 2015, I took on the role of coordinator &amp;amp; compiler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hamiltonnature.org/birding/counts/christmas-bird-count/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count (CBC)&lt;/a&gt;. Since that time I’ve been poring through the vast amounts of data accumulated over the decades. In a series of short posts, I explore how the Christmas Bird Count records can reveal some interesting facts about bird species in Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-brown-creeper--golden-crowned-kinglet&quot;&gt;Comparing Brown Creeper &amp;amp; Golden-crowned Kinglet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown Creepers and Golden-crowned Kinglets are not closely related, however they are both great examples of species found only in winter in Hamilton that are a challenge to find unless you are well-prepared to find them. Rarely would a non-birder ever notice a Brown Creeper, and to a lesser extent the same applies to Golden-crowned Kinglets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both species have several factors that make them more difficult to spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/golden-crowned-kinglet.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/golden-crowned-kinglet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/brown-creeper.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/brown-creeper.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Golden-crowned Kinglet &amp;amp; Brown Creeper.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown Creepers spend their time creeping up trees on the trunk and major branches, picking out hibernating insects &amp;amp; insect larvae from within bark crevices as food. They camouflage very well against the bark, enough to be unnoticable if it is either not right in front of you, or you don’t know how to look for them. They are also small, and have a song &amp;amp; call that are high pitched enough that it is not uncommon to meet older birders who can no longer hear them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golden-crowned Kinglets on the other hand, are found flocking together, often high in the treetops of deciduous trees, or anywhere in conifers, moving very quickly in and out of the shelter of the conifer. They are tiny (the smallest winter bird), and also have high-pitched calls that can be hard for some to hear. They feed on tiny caterpillars that somehow survive the winter in a frozen state – a fact only discovered reletively recently, in the early 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both, the best bet for finding and counting these species is by ear. When that isn’t practical, seeking out Black-capped Chickadee flocks in forested areas might reveal a mixed-species flock that might include one or both of these species. The kinglets will tend to group close together, and creepers will be in a flock that is spread across multiple trees, where they will climb up the trunk to near the top, then fly down to the bottom of the trunk of the next tree to climb up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/gcki-brcr.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s amazing in the Hamilton CBC data is that both species are regularly counted, and more or less line up with one another – when one is up, the other is up. If one is scarce, so is the other. They are not closely related, and do sometimes flock together in mixed-species flocks, but save for one year with a record count of kinglets, they line up well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reason I feel this chart is significant has nothing to do with the birds themselves however, it is that it demonstrates the consistent skills of the volunteer counters in the field. There are no years where these species were not found, and low years appear to be explained by very poor weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that the consistency of the chart over the decades shows that these species &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; have stable populations. To verify this, we can take a look at another chart, which takes into account the amount of effort put into counting birds as “count-per-hour”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/gcki-brcr-perhour.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we see is that the raw count data isn’t very misleading. There’s a couple spikes here, but otherwise it remains fairly consistent over time with perhaps a slightly below average count in the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Christmas Bird Count" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="Hamilton&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="bird records" /><summary type="html">How two tiny and elusive bird species can demonstrate the skill of Hamilton's Christmas Bird Count (CBC) volunteers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Arrival of the Carolina Wren: Hamilton CBC Stats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-carw/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Arrival of the Carolina Wren: Hamilton CBC Stats" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-carw</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-carw/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;In 2015, I took on the role of coordinator &amp;amp; compiler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hamiltonnature.org/birding/counts/christmas-bird-count/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count (CBC)&lt;/a&gt;. Since that time I’ve been poring through the vast amounts of data accumulated over the decades. In a series of short posts, I explore how the Christmas Bird Count records can reveal some interesting facts about bird species in Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carolina-wren.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carolina-wren.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Carolina Wren, Princess Point Park, Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;carolina-wren-a-non-migratory-resident&quot;&gt;Carolina Wren: A Non-Migratory Resident&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it was in the mid-2000s when I first heard a Carolina Wren. I had no idea what I was hearing – it was a very loud bird that was surprisingly elusive, and the only bird calls I knew well enough to identify a species were rural farm birds and common urban birds. It wasn’t until the rise of mobile birding apps, which had actual recordings of bird species, that I finally identified the loud little wren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I hadn’t really heard of this wren before, so where did it come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed the Carolina Wren has been pushing its territorial boundaries north for a few decades now. It is non-migratory – which means like some common birds we see year-round (Black-capped Chickadee, Northern Cardinal) – they generally do not migrate unless they need to find a new space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All other wren species known to either breed or overwinter in Hamilton are migratory: the aptly named Winter Wren, also-aptly-named Marsh Wren, the summer-abundant House Wren, and rare and unpredicatable Sedge Wren. (The Sedge Wren is probably the best example of a migratory pattern taken to the extreme: individuals are known to breed in completely different parts of the continent year-to-year, having little-to-no breeding site fidelity.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/marsh-wren.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/marsh-wren.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/sedge-wren.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/sedge-wren.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/house-wren.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/house-wren.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/winter-wren.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/winter-wren.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;Marsh Wren, Sedge Wren, House Wren, Winter Wren&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is also of note is that while Carolina Wrens are tiny and like to hide from view, they are not shy when it comes to singing. Like some other resident species, they can be heard singing in the winter. Black-capped Chickadee males are known to also do this, to sing loudly during the coldest days as a way of attracting a mate or reaffirming to a mate that they are strongly suited to not only enduring the winter, but thriving and singing through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard multiple Carolina Wrens singing loudly in -20°C weather in Hamilton. So there can be no doubt that when the Hamilton CBC data shows the rise in the count of Carolina Wrens, this is not due to the improved ability to find this species with the rise of digital cameras and birding apps, they do indeed call attention to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carw.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carw.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count Data, 1953-2015&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Winter Wren has been following a consistent ebb-and-flow pattern over the last 60 years, Carolina Wrens have been sporatically found in small numbers up until the late 1990s, and since then the count totals for this species have been taking off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, 2015 was the best year by far for this species, with a count of 64 individuals. The Carolina Wren quickly has surpassed the Winter Wren as the most common wren to find in Hamilton in the winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carolina-wren-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/carolina-wren-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Carolina Wren, Spencer Creek, Dundas, Ontario.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many more Carolina Wrens could the region be host to? Many of the individuals counted are concentrated within the Cootes-to-Escarpment area, where there is better shelter and presumably more food for these tiny birds. They are also known to visit feeders as well, which also helps sustain the populations through harsh winters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was presumed by some that the very harsh 2014-15 winter would cause a significant die-off of the population of Carolina Wrens, but the record showing in late 2015 might very well be proof that our local stock is finally hardy enough to endure the harshest of winters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while Hamilton was the most northerly range for this species, but it is still on the move northward. While non-migratory normally, as territories of pairs of birds are established some individuals are forced to move on to find territory elsewhere. One very ambitious individual was even found in Moosonee a couple years ago, though extreme migrants like that often do not establish breeding populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Christmas Bird Count" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="Carolina Wren" /><category term="Hamilton&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="bird records" /><summary type="html">How the Hamilton Christmas Bird Count data illustrates the establishment of a booming population of Carolina Wrens in Hamilton.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">eBird Histogramr</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/histogramr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="eBird Histogramr" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/histogramr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/histogramr/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ebird.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cornell’s eBird&lt;/a&gt; provides some fairly nifty looking bar graphs on &lt;a href=&quot;http://ebird.org/ebird/GuideMe?cmd=decisionPage&amp;amp;getLocations=hotspots&amp;amp;hotspots=L2093687&amp;amp;yr=all&amp;amp;m=&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hotspot locations&lt;/a&gt;, but while you can download the data in a raw format, that format is a fairly obscure one. This project converts this data into a much more familar format, CSV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two NPM modules so far, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ebird-histogramr&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ebird-histogramr-cli&lt;/code&gt;, the later being for general usage by anyone and the former for Node.js programmers looking to work with the data in a Javascript API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/ebird-histogramr-cli&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas. It currently requires some technical know-how to use, but I aim to improve that over time as the bugs get worked out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ebird" /><category term="birding" /><category term="CSV" /><category term="Node.js" /><category term="Javascript" /><category term="bird records" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><summary type="html">Convert eBird hotspot histograms into CSV files.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parser for Audubon’s Christmas Bird Count Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parser for Audubon's Christmas Bird Count Data" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser/">&lt;p&gt;The Audubon Society’s annual Christmas Bird Count (CBC) is the longest annual volunteer species count in the world, and has been going on since 1900. That means there’s a lot of data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone can &lt;a href=&quot;http://netapp.audubon.org/CBCObservation/Historical/ResultsByCount.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;download the data from the Audubon&lt;/a&gt; for personal or non-profit/academic use. However the data isn’t in the friendliest format around. While you can download the data in CSV, PDF, Excel, or XML format, the structure is very difficult to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data mixes total count records with other data points such as weather, participants, and the number of hours spent counting. Rather than spreadsheets with multiple pages seperating data, or splitting seperate kinds of data into separate files, everything is crammed into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I’ve written a parsing tool for using the historical CBC data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/audubon-cbc-cli&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas. It currently requires some technical know-how to use, but I aim to improve that over time as the bugs get worked out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="christmas bird count" /><category term="Audubon" /><category term="nature" /><category term="Node.js" /><category term="Javascript" /><category term="CSV" /><category term="bird records" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><summary type="html">Some tools for improving the usability of Audubon's CBC Data.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avitext 1.0, a Text File Format for Bird Observations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/avitext/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avitext 1.0, a Text File Format for Bird Observations" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/avitext</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/avitext/">&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/avitext-sample.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Avitext&lt;/b&gt; is a quick and easy way to record observations on your mobile device while in the field.&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avitext&lt;/strong&gt; is a plain text file format specification for bird species observations in the ABA region. It is designed to document checklists in the field as quickly as possible using a smartphone note-taking text application, such as iOS’s Notes or Google’s Keep app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It intends to fill a need for a method that is more easily transferrable than pen &amp;amp; paper without becoming as burdensome and slow as currently available record-keeping mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-work-in-progress&quot;&gt;A work in progress…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/avitext-spec&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="specifications" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><category term="mobile" /><summary type="html">A quick method for recording observations of bird species in the field on a mobile device with just a plain text note-taking app.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BirdBrain: A Bird Species in JSON Format</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/birdbrain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BirdBrain: A Bird Species in JSON Format" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/birdbrain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/birdbrain/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BirdBrain&lt;/strong&gt; is a simple Javascript library for interacting with avian species names and banding codes in the ABA region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now the API is quite simple, and the data is not fully optimized, so this library is quite large in size, and I do have some plans of making slimmed down versions that do not contain scientific names and make better use of more optimized JSON structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-more-info&quot;&gt;For more info…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/birdbrain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Javascript" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><category term="JSON" /><summary type="html">A JavaScript library for working with avian species names and banding codes in the ABA region.</summary></entry></feed>
