<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-27T15:08:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Rob Porter</title><subtitle>Digital Naturalist</subtitle><entry><title type="html">eBird Histogramr</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/histogramr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="eBird Histogramr" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/histogramr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/histogramr/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ebird.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cornell’s eBird&lt;/a&gt; provides some fairly nifty looking bar graphs on Hotspot locations, but while you can download the data in a raw format, that format is a fairly obscure one. This project converts this data into a much more familar format, CSV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two GitHub repositories so far, “ebird-histogramr” and “ebird-histogramr-cli”, the later being for general usage by anyone and the former for Node.js programmers looking to work with the data in a Javascript API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/ebird-histogramr-cli&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas. It currently requires some technical know-how to use, but I aim to improve that over time as the bugs get worked out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ebird" /><category term="birding" /><category term="bird records" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><summary type="html">Convert eBird hotspot histograms into CSV files.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parser for Audubon’s Christmas Bird Count Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parser for Audubon's Christmas Bird Count Data" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cbc-parser/">&lt;p&gt;Currently when downloading Christmas Bird Count data from the Audubon, the only available formats are quite difficult to work with. The XLS files are in a format that mixes bird records with data points such as weather, participants, and the number of hours spent counting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project aims to help anyone working with the data get a better grip on the actual raw bird records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/audubon-cbc-cli&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas. It currently requires some technical know-how to use, but I aim to improve that over time as the bugs get worked out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="christmas bird count" /><category term="Audubon" /><category term="nature" /><category term="bird records" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><summary type="html">A method for improving the usability of Audubon's CBC Data.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avitext 1.0, a Text File Format for Bird Observations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/avitext/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avitext 1.0, a Text File Format for Bird Observations" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/avitext</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/avitext/">&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/avitext-sample.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Avitext&lt;/b&gt; is a quick and easy way to record observations on your mobile device while in the field.&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avitext&lt;/strong&gt; is a plain text file format specification for bird species observations in the ABA region. It is designed to document checklists in the field as quickly as possible using a smartphone note-taking text application, such as iOS’s Notes or Google’s Keep app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/avitext-spec&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="specifications" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><category term="mobile" /><summary type="html">A quick method for recording observations of bird species in the field on a mobile device with just a plain text note-taking app.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BirdBrain: A Bird Species in JSON Format</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/birdbrain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BirdBrain: A Bird Species in JSON Format" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/birdbrain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/birdbrain/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BirdBrain&lt;/strong&gt; is a simple Javascript library for interacting with avian species names and banding codes in the ABA region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now the API is quite simple, and the data is not fully optimized, so this library is quite large in size, and I do have some plans of making slimmed down versions that do not contain scientific names and make better use of more optimized JSON structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more&quot;&gt;Read more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rgeraldporter/birdbrain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and can even comment or contribute ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="javascript" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="digital naturalist tools" /><category term="JSON" /><summary type="html">A JavaScript library for working with avian species names and banding codes in the ABA region.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hamilton CBC Head to Head: Kinglets &amp;amp; Creepers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hamilton CBC Head to Head: Kinglets &amp; Creepers" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cbc-stats-1/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I took on the role of coordinator &amp;amp; compiler of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hamiltonnature.org/birding/counts/christmas-bird-count/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hamilton Christmas Bird Count (CBC)&lt;/a&gt;. Since that time I’ve been poring through the vast amounts of data accumulated over the decades. In this series of posts, I explore how the Christmas Bird Count records can reveal some interesting facts about bird species in Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brown-creeper-vs-golden-crowned-kinglet&quot;&gt;Brown Creeper vs Golden-crowned Kinglet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/golden-crowned-kinglet.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:33%; padding:0.667em;padding-left:0;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brown Creeper and Golden-crowned Kinglets are not closely related, however they are both great examples of winter-only species in Hamilton that are a challenge to find unless you are well-versed in finding them. Rarely would a non-birder ever notice a Brown Creeper, and to a lesser extent, the same applies to Golden-crowned Kinglets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both species have several factors that make them more difficult to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/brown-creeper.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:33%; padding:0.667em;padding-right:0;padding-top:0;&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown Creepers spend their time creeping up trees on the trunk and major branches, picking out hibernating insects &amp;amp; insect larvae from within bark crevices. They camouflage very well against the bark, enough to be unnoticable if it is either not right in front of you, or you don’t know how to look for them. They are also small, and have a song &amp;amp; call that are high pitched enough that it is not uncommon to meet older birders who can no longer hear them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golden-crowned Kinglets on the other hand, are found flocking together, often high in the treetops of deciduous trees, or anywhere in conifers, moving very quickly in and out of the shelter of the conifer. They are tiny (the smallest winter bird), and also have high-pitched calls that can be hard for some to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both, the best bet for finding and counting these species is by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/gcki-brcr.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s amazing in the Hamilton CBC data is that both species are regularly counted, and more or less line up with one another – when one is up, the other is up. If one is scarce, so is the other. They are not related at all, and do sometimes flock together in mixed-species flocks, but save for one year with a record-count of kinglets, they line up well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reason I feel this chart is significant has nothing to do with the birds themselves, however, it is that it demonstrates the consistent skills of the volunteer counters in the field. There are no years where these species were not found, and low years appear to be explained by poor weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that the consistency of the chart over the decades shows that these species &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; have stable populations. I qualify with “may” is this chart reflect raw data that does not take into account the variable number of volunteer hours spent counting each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for that we look at average count of each species per volunteer hour….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/cbc-onha/gcki-brcr-perhour.png&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart shows that the raw count data isn’t very misleading. There’s a couple spikes here, but otherwise it remains fairly consistent over time with perhaps a slightly below average count in the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="birding" /><category term="Christmas Bird Count" /><category term="nature" /><category term="ornithology" /><category term="Hamilton&amp;#44; Ontario" /><category term="bird records" /><summary type="html">How two tiny and elusive bird species can demonstrate the skill of Hamilton's Christmas Bird Count (CBC) volunteers</summary></entry></feed>
